A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Division, Office Files of John S. Nagel FA719
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, International Division, Office Files of John S. Nagel
1966-1975
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA719
1.32 Cubic Feet
The International Division Papers of John S. Nagel document his activities and a number of those of the International Division's Latin America and Caribbean (ID/LAC) office for the period 1966 to 1975. The papers were accessioned into the Archives in two stages: Series I, Population Files, 1966-1972, were transferred to the Archives in February 1982; Series II, Correspondence Files, 1968-1975, were removed from terminated office files shipped to New York for permanent storage from the Mexico City field office in March 1978. These papers consist of copies of correspondence, inter-office memoranda, and reports. Arrangement within each series corresponds as closely as possible to the original order established by Nagel's New York and Mexico City offices.
Conditions Governing Access
Material more than ten years old is open for scholarly research.
Select individual files are restricted, as noted. Permission to access these files must be obtained from the Ford Foundation before scholarly access is permitted.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be restricted from scholarly research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment.
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be restricted from scholarly research at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/RAC Head of Reference.
Separated Materials
Staff and consultant reports and publications have been pulled and accessioned into the FF Archives. A cross-reference sheet located within the folders denotes accessioned reports. A list of titles removed from the papers is appended to this register. Papers not related to Ford Foundation activities have been removed.
Biographical / Historical
John S. Nagel, Ford Foundation Program Advisor in Population for the Latin America and Caribbean office of the International Division, was a member of the Foundation staff from 1962 until his retirement in 1977. During this period, he held the following positions:
• April 1973, Program Advisor, LA&C, Mexico City, ID • September 1968, Deputy and Program Officer, LA&C, New York, ID • June 1966, Representative, LA&C, Argentina, ID • June 1965, Representative, LA&C, Argentina and Chile, OD • July 1962, Representative, LA&C, Mexico and Central America, Mexico City, OD • January 1962, Associate Director, LA&C, New York, OD
Mr. Nagel also served as a consultant to the Ford Foundation on two separate occassions following his retirement. From June 1977 until December 1978, he monitored and evaluated program activities in the field of population for the LA&C office; and from November 1979 until September 1980, he served in the Population Program on communications projects.
John Nagel was born June 5, 1913. He received his B.S. degree in Commerce from Northwestern University in 1934.
Prior to Nagel's career with the Ford Foundation, he held the following positions:
• 1953-1961, Needham, Louis & Brorby, Director of Marketing; V.P. and Account Supervisor • 1948-1953, Young & Rubicam, Marketing and Account Executive • 1943-1948, Booz, Allen & Hamilton, Staff Manager and Director of Executive Personnel Recruitment • 1941-1943, Zurich Insurance, Sales Promotion Manager and Assistant Director of Public Relations • 1936-1941, Northwestern University, Director of Alumni Relations and Assistant to Vice President in Charge of Production
After his retirement and consultantcies with the Foundation, Mr. Nagel moved to Naples, Florida.
Scope and Contents
The three boxes of correspondence, inter-office memoranda, and reports which constitute the International Division Papers of John S. Nagel, document his activities and a number of those of the Foundation's Latin America and Caribbean (LAC) office for the years 1966 to 1975.
The papers, which are broad in scope, yet lacking in quantity and depth, contain material on Foundation sponsored population projects including the Bellagio Population Group; the International Agency for Contraceptive Research and Development; the International Planned Parenthood Federation; and the Pan American Health Organization. The material consists of reports and related correspondence. The papers are indicative of the role Nagel played within the Latin America and Caribbean program.
The correspondence files document the day-to-day program activity and other Foundation related correspondence of Nagel for the period 1966 to 1975.
Arrangement
The International Division Papers of John S. Nagel are divided into two series:
I. Population Files, 1966-1972 II. Chronological Files, 1968-1975
Ford Foundation
- Population Files, 1966-1972; I
  Arrangement
  Series I, Population Files (1966-1972), is the most substantive. It contains population files arranged in alphabetical order by subject. Printed matter consists of correspondence, inter-office memoranda, and reports. Within each folder, the files are arranged in reverse chronological order.
  - ACORD - International Agency for Contraceptive Research and Development, 1970 May - 1969 December (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bellagio Population Group, 1971 July - 1969 July (Box 1, Folder 2-5)
  - Ford Foundation Program in Reproductive Biology, 1972 January (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Inter-American Development Bank, 1971 March - 1969 November (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - International Planned Parenthood Federation, 1971 May - 1969 September (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Nutrition, 1970 December (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - OAS - PAHO, 1970 May - 1969 February (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Population Advisor Mailings, 1972 September - 1971 December (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Population Council, 1970 June - 1969 April (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Population Strategy - Trustees, 1970 November - July (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - University of California, 1968 August (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - University of Chicago, 1971 June - 1966 February (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - University of Michigan, 1969 January - 1967 December (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - UNC Population Center, 1970 October - 1969 May (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Chronological Files, 1968-1975; II
  Series II, Chronological Files (1968-1975), is the most extensive. It contains two subject files and copies of Nagel's outgoing correspondence and inter-office memoranda with FF colleagues, grantee organizations, and individuals and oraganizations seeking grants. The files are arranged in reverse calendar order. Within each folder, the papers are arranged in reverse chronological order.
  - Grant Action Guidelines, 1972 November - June (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Legal Basis for Overseas Activities, 1970 November - September (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - 1975 May - April (Box 2, Folder 20-21)
  - 1974 February (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - 1973 (Box 2, Folder 23-34)
  - 1972 (Box 2, Folder 35-46)
  - 1971 (Box 3, Folder 47-58)
  - 1970 (Box 3, Folder 59-70)
  - 1969 (Box 3, Folder 71-81)
  - 1968 (Box 3, Folder 82-87)
- Appendix A: FF Reports Accessioned
  The following list of unpublished reports written by FF staff and consultants were removed from the papers. They are listed alphabetically by author. For each author, the reports are arranged in alphabetical order. The number at the left, is the assigned accession number. They have been transferred to the Foundation's Archives collection of staff and consultant reports.
  - Bell, David. The Commitment of Leaders, 1971 April (Report 3858)
  - Bell, David. Follow-up to the Bellagio Meetings on Population and Agriculture: More International Research Centers?, 1970 June 25 (Report 4876)
  - Bell, David. International Division Meeting, Beirut, January 9-11, 1967 - Summary Notes, 1967 January 31 (Report 8901)
  - Bell, David. Summary of Bellagio Population Conference, June 13-16, 1971, 1971 June (Report 9120)
  - Blomberg, Robert. Recommendations to Steering Committee of Bellagio Population Group, 1970 November 3 (Report 9550)
  - Ford Foundation. Background Material for A Meeting to Review the Ford Foundation Program in Reproductive Biology. Volumes I & II, 1972 January 6 - 7 (Report 9554)
  - Ford Foundation. Ford Foundation Submission to Interim Committee - Bellagio Population Group September 10, 1970, 1970 September 10 (Report 4986)
  - Ford Foundation. Interim Report on Surveys of Social and Management Sciences Relevant to Population Problems, 1971 June 10 (Report 9545)
  - Ford Foundation. Statement on Legal Basis for the International Activities of the Ford Foundation, 1970 September 15 (Report 2401)
  - Harkavy, Oscar. Informal Notes on Bellagio Population Conference Discussion, 1971 June 24 (Report 9549)
  - Harkavy, Oscar. Recommendations to Steering Committee of Bellagio Population Group. Draft, 1970 September 21 (Report 9546)
  - Harkavy, Oscar. Research in Reproductive Biology and Contraceptive Technology: Present Status and Needs for the Future, 1970 April 6 - 8 (Report 9552)
  - Harkavy, Oscar. Second Conference of AID Administrators in Field of Population 18 November 1969, 1969 November 18 (Report 9553)
  - Hill, Forrest. Overseas Development Program: Guide for Overseas Development Actions, 1964 June 1 (Report 2484)
  - Nagel, John S. Comments on Draft Action Guidelines, 1972 June 29 (Report 9548)
  - Nagel, John S. Draft Guidelines for Grants to Organizations, 1972 November 21 (Report 9547)
  - Simmons, Ozzie. Comments on Bellagio Papers, 1970 November 12 (Report 9551)
  - Strasburg, Paul. Malnutrition in Latin America: Recommendations ford Ford Foundation Support of Research and Training in Human Nutrition, 1970 December (Report 3814)
  - Sutton, Francis. Draft Strategy Paper on Population, 1970 August 3 (Report 5502)